<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>By the Maior. A proclamation for the reformation of abuses, in the Gaole of Nevv-gate</title>
            <title>Proclamations. 1617-09-23</title>
            <author>City of London (England). Lord Mayor.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1617</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 6 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 3 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A72779</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 16727.1</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S125087</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99900365</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99900365</idno>
            <idno type="VID">151036</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A72779)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 151036)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1997:8)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>By the Maior. A proclamation for the reformation of abuses, in the Gaole of Nevv-gate</title>
                  <title>Proclamations. 1617-09-23</title>
                  <author>City of London (England). Lord Mayor.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>2 sheets (versos blank)   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by VVilliam Iaggard, printer to the Honourable Citie of London,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1617.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>See also STC 16733.3--STC.</note>
                  <note>Dated at end: ... at Guildhall, the xxiij. day of September, in the yeere of our Lord God, 1617.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Guildhall Library, London, England.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Prisons --  Law and legislation --  England --  London --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>London (England) --  History --  17th century --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="mayoral_proclamation">
            <pb facs="tcp:151036:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <opener>
               <signed>I. L.</signed>
            </opener>
            <head>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>blazon of the City of London</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </head>
            <head>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> By the Maior.</head>
            <head type="sub">A Proclamation for Reformation of abuſes, in the Gaole of New-gate.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hereas of late, notorious Mutinies and Out-rages haue bin committed by the Priſoners within the Gaole of Newgate, which is conceyued to grow through the negligence of the Keepers, ſuffering their Priſoners to become drunke and diſordered, permitting them wine, Tobacco, exceſſiue ſtrong drinke, gaming, and reſort of Women of lewd behauiour. By reaſon of which libertie, diſſolute and lewd perſonnes, who commit Thefts and Robberies, take a kind of comfort, and ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther heart in the ſaide Gaole, and are in ſome ſort inci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to commit Fellonies, vpon hope of the lewd Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, and ſuch lewd Comforts as they finde in the ſaid Gaole. For Reformation whereof, and to preuent aſwell all manner Oppreſſion in the Gaolers, and li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centiouſneſſe of Priſoners: and to the end henceforth to take away all manner of hope in ſuch as ſhall be thither ſent for offences, that they ſhall not finde ſuch lewd and ſhamefull comforts as they haue heeretofore there found, and to the end, to containe the Priſoners within a diſcipline, that Mutinies and Inſolencies may bee pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uented.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Firſt, It is thought fit, ordered, and Commanded by the Lord Maior and Court of Aldermen, That the Maſter of the ſame Gaole, bee attendant himſelfe vpon the ſaid Gaole, and that the ſame be not Farmed out, directly, nor by any manner cunning or indirect meane whatſoeuer.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Secondly, That the Gaoler, Keepers, Seruants, or vnder Officers, ſhall not permit or ſuffer any Beere or Ale to bee receiued or brought into the ſaide Gaole or Priſon, but onely of the price of eight ſhillings the barrell, or of foure ſhillings the barrell, nor ſuffer the diſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute ſort of Priſoners in the Common gaole, to haue any wine at all to be brought vnto them.</p>
            <p n="3">3 Thirdly, that there be a full Ale-quart of eight ſhillings Beere or Ale ſolde for a peny, and ſo deliuered to the Priſoners, and according to that rate, pint or halfe pint: and the like meaſure of foure ſhillings Beere or Ale for a halfe peny: and that the Priſoners haue Bread and all other Victuals according to the aſſize, and at vſuall and common prizes, and that there be no oppreſſion or exaction for their beds or lodging.</p>
            <p n="4">4 Fourthly, that the Gaoler, Keepers, Seruants, or vnder Officers in the ſaide gaole, ſhall not ſuffer the taking of Tobacco by the diſſolute ſort of priſoners in the common gaole: and to that end ſhall ſearch and view all whatſoeuer that ſhall be brought into the ſaid priſon for the vſe of any priſoner there, that no Tobacco nor Tobacco-pipes, Candles, or other things to fire their Tobacco be brought to them.</p>
            <p n="5">5 Fiftly, That the ſaide Gaolers, keepers, ſeruants, or vnder Officers, do take ſuch care, and vſe ſuch diligence, that the men priſoners and women priſoners bee kept aſunder, and not ſuffered to come together in anie part of the ſaide priſon, except it be at the time of diuine Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice, receiuing of the Sacrament, or hearing of Sermons.</p>
            <p n="6">6 Sixtly, that the ſaid Gaoler, keepers, ſeruants, or vnder Officers, ſhall not take any fee of any Priſoner committed for Fellony, or ſuſpition of Fellony, nor of any perſon that ſhall haue occaſion to come or reſort to them or to any of them, to bring them meate, drink, or other needfull prouiſions, for, or in reſpect onely of turning of the key, or opening the doore for ſuch perſon bringing ſuch prouiſion to any priſoner.</p>
            <p n="7">7 Seuenthly, That the ſaide Gaoler, keepers, Seruants, or vnder Officers, ſhal not ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer any woman to be with any man<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 chunk">
                  <desc>…</desc>
               </gap> priſoner alone in the priſon, but onely the Wife, Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, Siſter, or neere kinſwoman of ſuch priſoner, and ſo knowne to the keeper before ſhe bee admitted.</p>
            <p n="8">8 Eightly, that the ſaide gaoler, keepers, ſeruants, or vnder Officers, ſhall take no Fees for, or in reſpect of releaſe or eaſe of Irons, but ſuch as at his perill hee may lawfully iuſtifye and auow.</p>
            <p n="9">
               <pb facs="tcp:151036:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
9 Ninthly, that if any Priſoners mutiny, or bee inſolent, or ſhall harten or giue euill ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample to others, in ſtirring other priſoners in word or deede to mutiny, that then ſuch priſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner ſo offending, be loaden with more Irons, and that he be put into the Dungeon, or other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe chaſtized in the diſcretion of the Maſter keeper, ſo as the ſame chaſticement tend not to the loſſe of uſe or limbe.</p>
            <p n="10">10 Tenthly, for auoyding quarrelles in the gaole, that no priſoner bee permitted to play in the ſaide gaole, at Cards, Dice, or any other game whatſoeuer.</p>
            <p n="11">11 Eleuenthly, Whereas there hath beene heeretofore vſed a drunken manner of Garniſh in Wine or other ſtrong drinke, by all ſuch priſoners as go to the Maiſters ſide at theyr firſt commitment to Newgate: It is ordered and thought fit that the ſame vſage bee vtterly put downe and diſallowed, and to be henceforth no more vſed.</p>
            <p n="12">12 Laſtly, That the gaoler nor any of the vnder-keepers do take aboue twelue pence for any one times attendance with any Priſoner, when the ſame Priſoner is by Commandement of any Iuſtice of Peace to bee brought before him.</p>
            <p>The Gaoler offending in any of the Premiſſes, ſhall for the firſt offence forfeyte and pay twenty pounds, and for the ſecond offence forty poundes, and for the third offence to loſe his place, and to bee for euer diſabled to keepe that gaole or any other gaole, within the Citie of London, and the Liberties thereof.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Dated at the Guildhall, <date>the xxiij. day of September, in the yeere of our Lord God, 1617.</date>
               </dateline>
               <lb/>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> God ſaue the King. <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>Printed by William Iaggard, Printer to the Honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Citie of London. 1617.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:151036:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
